A Guide to the Correspondence of Joseph C. Cabell
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Correspondence of Joseph C. Cabell
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13923
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the University of Virginia Library, from William F. Muller, Smithfield Road., Charlottesville, Virginia, on July 9, 2007.
Scope and Content
The correspondence of Joseph C. Cabell, ca. 280 items (1 Hollinger box, .5 linear feet), ca. 1807-1856, deals chiefly with family news and business matters including topics such as improvements to "Edgewood" (Dr. George Cabell, Jr., March 4, 1811); Samuel Cabell at the College of William and Mary (October 11 and November 28, 1807), medical advice from Dr. George Cabell (November 13 and 30, 1814), and the weights of the hogs belonging to the "Negroes' from "Belmont" (William N. Dixon, December 21, 1850). Correspondents include Dr. John Grattan Cabell, Henry Coalter Cabell, Mayo Cabell, Andrew Duncan, David S. G. Cabell, Colonel William Cabell, Dr. George Cabell, Jr. and James Bruce McClelland. Many letters deal with business concerns, the manufacture and procurement of equipment for Cabell, recommendation of workers and overseers, crops, Cabell's flour mill, and land sales. There also present are some purely financial and legal documents and these have been filed under the pertinent name.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by name of correspondent, with those containing few items placed in miscellaneous correspondent folders together. Often these have only one or two items per name, so the dates for these correspondents are not mentioned separately in the guide.
Contents List
- 1822-1855 Correspondence - A through C (Miscellaneous Correspondents), most of this correspondence pertains to the business interests of Joseph C. Cabell and correspondents include: John A. Allen; Peter F. Ayres; Nathan J. Barrett; R.K. Bibb; Harrison Bryant; A. Bryce; David J. Burr; Dr. George Callaway; Dr. Paul C. Callaway (1815-1876) who writes concerning the suitability of Mr. Scruggs as an overseer (July 8 and 10, 1853); Patrick B. Carter; W[illiam] G. Clarke; and P.W. Coffee (Box-folder 1:1)
- 1808-1856 Correspondence - Cabell Family, most of this correspondence pertains to the business interests of Joseph C. Cabell and correspondents include: Clifford Cabell; Edward A. Cabell who discusses claims of the Higginbotham legatees for Colonel Higginbotham's Revolutionary War service, and the spring election, involving Mr. Gordon (February 11, 1833); G.W. Cabell; John Cabell, Sr.; Joseph C. Cabell writes concerning his opinion of religion (May 3, 1852); and the financial scam pulled by Addison and St. Clair Hartman in the area (January 26, 1855); [Dr. L.J. Cabell?] about the health of Oscar, [a slave?] (October 30, 1817); Mary W. Cabell: M.C[abell?]; N.F. Cabell shares his concern over his aunt's misunderstanding of his comments about his uncle's will (April 26, 1856); Nicholas M. Cabell; Patrick H. Cabell praises Joseph C. Cabell's educational pamphlet (July 5, 1825) and his pamphlet about constitutional doctrines (November 17, 1831) and describes his trip to Montgomery (November 17, 1831); Paul Cabell discusses Joseph C. Cabell's missing letter from Mr. Madison (October 5, 1827); [P.R.?] Cabell; W.D. Cabell; William H. Cabell; William M. Cabell; and William S. Cabell concerning an account for medical services for a slave belonging to Joseph C. Cabell (March 1, 1815) (Box-folder 1:2)
- 1852-1855 Correspondence - David S.G. Cabell, conducts some legal business for Joseph C. Cabell, recording a deed for land in Amherst County Court (October 28, 1854); sends tax bills due from Nicholas Cabell's estate, sheriffs bills, and clerk's bills (November 24, 1854); and his account with Cabell (January 1, 1855) (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1811-1821 Correspondence - Dr. George Cabell, Jr. (1774-1827) of "Bon Aire" writes concerning many family and business affairs, including: improvements at Edgewood (March 4, 1811); concerns over his own wheat harvest (June 1, 1814); illness of slaves at the "S. B. farm" (November 13 and 30, 1814); other references to "S.B. farm" (November 23, 1811); and improvements at his farm "Bon Aire" (October 22, 1817) (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1814-1815 Correspondence - Dr. George Cabell, Sr. writes for advice and help concerning his efforts toward the reinstatement of his son, George, at Princeton University (June 20, 1814 and April 17, 1815) (Box-folder 1:5)
- 1849-1855 Correspondence -Henry Coalter Cabell (1820-1889), nephew of Joseph C. Cabell, writes about the stock and affairs of the James River and Kanawha River Company (July 22, 1849; February 26, 1853); his upcoming marriage (March 8, 1850); the distress of his wife, Jane Alston, over the death of her [father, Major James Alston, Abbeville, South Carolina?] and the poor health of his own father, William Henry Cabell (January 8, 1851); and the death of his brother Grattan's wife [Sarah Marshall Tankersley?] (March 17, 1855) (Box-folder 1:6)
- 1844-1851 Correspondence - John Grattan Cabell (1817-1896), nephew of Joseph C. Cabell, many of his letters relate his progress in carrying out Joseph C. Cabell's purchases and other requests in Richmond and the settling of his accounts; other topics include: dangers of cholera in Richmond, especially among the tenements in the Basin area (June 7, 1849); arrangements to pay the passage for a slave, Shandy, to Midway Mills and provide him with a pass (June 16, 1849); directions for the measurement of a truss for old Phil [a slave?], if the one sent does not suit (March 17, 1850); date of the wedding of Henry C. Cabell set (April 9, 1850); the serious decline in the health of his father (December 8, 10, 13, 1850); and his improvement (January 6 and 14, 1851); and the visit of the family to Huguenot Springs and a request from Katy, a slave belonging to Joseph C. Cabell, for a pass to visit her child at "Corotoman" with her husband (September 12, 1851) (Box-folder 1:7)
- 1852-1855 Correspondence - John Grattan Cabell (1817-1896), nephew of Joseph C. Cabell, many of his letters relate his progress in carrying out Joseph C. Cabell's purchases and other requests in Richmond and the settling of his accounts; other topics include: the serious illness of Edward Mayo, Julia Cabell's brother (June 4, 1852); the actions of the Democrats in the Virginia State Legislature (December 6, 1852); reference to the death of his father (January 26, 1853); information about the type of glass available for purchase (February 2, 9, and 14, 1853); discussion about his plans for a press for books and papers (March 14, 1853); presence of cholera among the Negroes and the death of the grandchild of the slave, Katy (July 23, 1854); Coalter and his wife had a daughter (September 25, 1854); Julia leaves for her trip to Europe accompanied by a nephew (October 8, 1854); Carrington [Cabell?] named President of a railroad that travels from Tallahassee to the Georgia line (August 7, 1855); his impressions of the State Fair (November 3, 1855) (Box-folder 1:8)
- 1822-1832 Correspondence - Mayo Cabell of "Union Hill" (1800-1869), generally writes concerning the business affairs of Joseph C. Cabell, including: procurement of boats to transport his wheat (October 10, 11, 20, 1823); his willingness to try a new kind of seed remarking upon the success of General Cocke with his wheat (August 12, 1825); and Mr. Bullock's request for 10-15 bushels of Cabell's white Mexican wheat (September 18, 1826) (Box-folder 1:9)
- 1840-1855 Correspondence - Mayo Cabell of "Union Hill" (1800-1869), generally writes concerning the business affairs of Joseph C. Cabell, including: the contract for keeping a ferry at New Market and the birth of a daughter [Cornelia Mayo Cabell ?] to Mayo and his wife, Cornelia (July 31, 1840); wishes for Joseph C. Cabell's success with "the further improvement of the James River, before the Legislature of Virginia this winter" (November 8, 1841); description of the circumstances of the "chastisement" of Jim Brown by Mr. Mathews, the carpenter at "Midway" plantation (February 2, 1844); business questions concerning grinding wheat and meal at Joseph C. Cabell's mill (January 10 and 27, 1848); the establishment of a savings bank at New Market (July 27, 1853) (Box-folder 1:10)
- 1807-1825 Correspondence - Samuel J. Cabell, Jr. of "Soldier's Joy" writes concerning the possible costs of attending William and Mary College (October 11 and November 28, 1807); a controversy between Joseph C. Cabell and a Mr. Bowles (July 30, 1810, 2 letters); his delight at the "brightening prospects of the University [of Virginia]" (March 10, 1825) (Box-folder 1:11)
- 1810-1816 Correspondence - Colonel Samuel J. Cabell (1756-1818) of "Soldier's Joy" writes about the illness of his daughter Peggy (September 12, 1815); mentions a planned visit to General John Cropper and his request to Joseph C. Cabell for his help in securing a sign painter to inscribe a tribute to his wife, Sarah Cabell, on a tablet affixed to a pyramid as a sign of his deep affection for his wife, which he writes out in full in his letter (December 12, 1816) (Box-folder 1:12)
- 1811-1817 Correspondence - Colonel William Cabell writes chiefly about family and business matters, especially whether Joseph Cabell intends to keep Hudnall as overseer of the Liberty Hall estate (July 30, 1813); mentions Essex and Randolph who are working for Joseph C. Cabell as [sawyers ?] (June 23, 1816); and requests that he vote in proxy for him in the stockholders meeting of the Virginia Bank and the Farmer's Bank in Richmond (December 10, 1817) (Box-folder 1:13)
- 1824-1855 Correspondence - D through M (Miscellaneous Correspondents), most of this correspondence pertains to the business interests of Joseph C. Cabell and correspondents include: William Dennis; William N. Dixon; H.W. Dwight; Reuben Elsome; William J. Ewers writes concerning sickness among the slaves (June 1, 1855); William Gordon; Miss Graff; D.W. Kendrick agrees to take one of Cabell's coopers to train in the wheelwright business (January 30, 1847) and asks for an adjustment in the hire price for Patrick (April 17, 1847); E.C. Lankford; Samuel Law describes his journey back to Pittsfield, Massachusetts and the improvements in agricultural tools that he has seen (December 20, 1824); Alexander Moseley; and John W. Mosby gives a detailed appraisal of the value of some land that Cabell wants to exchange (August 31, 1848) (Box-folder 1:14)
- 1821-1833 Correspondence - Andrew Duncan, a machinist working for John Hartwell Cocke, mentions his work at John Hartwell Cocke's plantation "Bremo" (June 14, 1821 and July 30, 1825); he also describes his "machines" and sends requests for monetary help with his debts in several letters (Box-folder 1:15)
- 1834-1855 Correspondence - McClelland Family, including one letter from Sarah Cabell McClelland (1822-1858); eleven letters from Thomas Stanhope McClelland (1810-1893) of "Montezuma" writes concerning a recommendation for Johnson, a piano maker and tuner (September 30, 1834); a survey of Warminster Road by Mr. Livermore and other engineers who believe it would provide a good location for the canal (August 7, 1835); a discussion of the local elections in Buckingham County and Nelson County (April 15, 1834); plans to go to New Orleans or Texas (September 22, 1847); his plans to build a house and his need for Toby [a mason?] working for Joseph C. Cabell (April 6 and August 1, 1849); offer to sell the Welsh Rock property (October 12, 1850); and his lands in Texas (March 20, 1851); and eleven letters from James Bruce McClelland (1827-1862) who mentions his purchase of the Welsh Rock tract of land and its uses (June 11 and July 2, 1851); questions about selling stock of the James River and Kanawha Company (October 20, 1851); and McClelland's request to "borrow" his carpenter, Mr. Mathews, to help build a tobacco factory (November 2 and 7, 1852) (Box-folder 1:16)
- 1814-1855 Correspondence - N through Z (Miscellaneous Correspondents), most of this correspondence pertains to the business interests of Joseph C. Cabell and correspondents include: Messrs. Parker & Smith, Richmond, Virginia; James W. Phillips; John Pryor; Douglas Puckett; Joseph H. Roberts; Roderick Taliaferro; L.N. Tazewell's diagram of a [horse?] mill (December 20, 1820); J.B. Thomas; Paul Tillman reports on his affairs at Warminster (December 1814); Walter Timberlake; John Tyler introduces his nephews, Addison and St. Clair Hartman who are doing business in the area (July 9, 1853), for more about them also see Joseph C. Cabell (January 26, 1855); Unidentified (receipt and damaged letter); and John Watson (Box-folder 1:17)
- 1818-1832 Correspondence - Samuel P. Parsons, Virginia Superintendent of the Penitentiary, writes about manufacturing a plough for Cabell and other tools such as spinning wheels, cart wheels, various saws, and other agricultural matters (1818-1823); and a discussion of the Virginia Legislature and its action on the incorporation of the James River and Kanawha Company (March 20, 1832) (Box-folder 1:18)